Finding Aid for Office of the Vice President for Research (University of Michigan), Records, 1950-2001
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- OVPR Financial and Administrative Files
  - Financial Files
    - Budget Conferences, Proposals, and Presentations
      - Fiscal Year, 1987-1988
        - Office of Energy Research (Box 146)
        - Office of the Vice President for Research (OVPR) (Box 146)
        - Philological Research (Middle English Dictionary) (Box 146)
        - Proposal to Provost and Related Correspondence (Box 146)
        - Protein Structure and Design Program (Box 146)
        - Radiation Control Service (Box 146)
        - Statistical Research Laboratory (Box 146)
        - Unit for Laboratory Animal Medicine (ULAM) (Box 146)
      - Fiscal Year, 1988-1989
        - General (Box 147)
        - Institute of Science and Technology (IST) (Box 147)
        - Office of Energy Research (Box 147)
        - Proposal to Provost (Box 147)
      - Fiscal Year, 1989-1990
        - Division of Research Development and Administration (DRDA) (Box 147)
      - Fiscal Year (cont.), 1989-1990 (Box 147)
        - General (Box 147)
        - Institute for Social Research (ISR) (Box 147)
        - Institute of Science and Technology (IST) (Box 147)
        - Intellectual Properties Office (IPO) (Box 147)
        - Michigan Memorial Phoenix Project (Box 147)
        - Middle English Dictionary (MED) (Box 147)
        - Neuroscience Laboratory (Box 147)
        - Protein Structure and Design Program (Box 147)
        - Statistical Research Laboratory (Box 147)
        - University of Michigan Transportation Research Institute (UMTRI) (Box 147)
        - Unit for Laboratory Animal Medicine (ULAM) (Box 147)
      - Fiscal Year, 1990-1991
        - Budget Presentation to Provost (Box 147)
        - Biophysics Research Division (BRD) (Box 147)
        - Center for Human Growth and Development (Box 147)
        - Center for Molecular Genetics (Box 147)
        - Division of Research Development and Administration (DRDA) (Box 147)
        - Institute for Social Research (ISR) (Box 147)
        - Institute of Gerontology (IoG) (Box 147)
        - Institute of Labor and Industrial Relations (ILIR) (Box 147)
        - Intellectual Properties Office (IPO) (Box 147)
        - Michigan Memorial Phoenix Project (Box 147)
        - Middle English Dictionary (MED) (Box 147)
        - Neuroscience Laboratory (Box 147)
        - Protein Structure and Design Program (Box 147)
        - Reproductive Sciences Program (Box 147)
        - Statistical Research Laboratory (Box 147)
        - University of Michigan Transportation Research Institute (UMTRI) (Box 147)
        - Unit for Laboratory Animal Medicine (ULAM) (Box 147)
      - Fiscal Year, 1991-1992
        - Budget Meeting with Provost (Box 147)
        - Division of Research Development and Administration (DRDA) (Box 147)
        - General (Box 147)
        - Intellectual Properties Office (IPO) (Box 147)
        - Program in Evolution and Human Behavior (EHB) (Box 147)
        - Protein Structure and Design Program (Box 147)
        - University of Michigan Transportation Research Institute (UMTRI) (Box 147)
      - Fiscal Year General, 1992-1993 (Box 147)
      - Fiscal Year General, 1993-1994 (Box 147)
      - Fiscal Year General, 1994-1995 (Box 147)
      - Fiscal Year, 1995-1996 (Box 147)
        - Center for Human Growth and Development (Box 147)
        - Center for Statistical Consultation and Research (CSCAR) (Box 147)
        - Division of Research Development and Administration (DRDA) (Box 148)
        - General (Box 148)
        - Institute for Social Research (ISR) (Box 148)
        - Institute of Gerontology (IoG) (Box 148)
        - Michigan Memorial Phoenix Project (Box 148)
        - Middle English Dictionary (MED) (Box 148)
        - Neuroscience Laboratory (Box 148)
        - Reproductive Sciences Program (RSP) (Box 148)
        - Technology Management Office (TMO) (Box 148)
        - University of Michigan Transportation Research Institute (UMTRI) (Box 148)
        - Unit for Laboratory Animal Medicine (ULAM) (Box 148)
      - Fiscal Year General, 1996-1997 (Box 148)
      - Fiscal Year General, 1997-1998 (Box 148)
      - Fiscal Year General, 1998-1999 (Box 148)
      - Miscellaneous FIles, 1982-1995 (Box 148)
        - Budget Reduction Plans (5-Year Plans), 1982-1984 (Box 148)
        - Cost Accounting Standards, 1997 (Box 148)
        - Cost Accounting Standards Core Group, 1995 (Box 148)
        - Cost Sharing, 1987-1988 (Box 148)
        - Internal Research Funding Team, 1994-1995 (Box 148)
- Administrative Files, 1987-1999
  The Administrative Files 1987-1999 (1.5 linear feet), contain information related to the day-to-day administration within the OVPR and its reporting units. Of particular interest are the Unit Oversight Meetings Files, which contain materials related to regular meetings regarding the administration of OVPR's reporting units. Also of interest are annual reports prepared by OVPR describing the prior year's activities, as well as reports to the Board of Regents.
  - Annual Reports, 1990-1993; 1998; 3 folders (Box 149)
  - Chalkboard (Online Discussion Board), 1996 (Box 149)
  - Communications Initiative, 1996 (Box 149)
  - Establishment of Centers and Institutes, 1987-1989 (Box 149)
  - Mission Statement, 1992 (Box 149)
  - Organizational Structure
    - Report of the Planning Committee for the Merger, 1984 (Box 149)
    - Reorganization, 1989-1990 (Box 149)
  - OVPR/Development Interface (Box 149)
  - Regents Reports, 1994; 1997-1998 (Box 149)
  - Research Funding Projections, 1996 (Box 149)
  - Research Unit Activity Profiles (Describe Units and Responsibilities), 1999 (Box 149)
  - Retreats
    - General, 1988-1990 (Box 149)
    - Mini-Retreat on Integrity, 1993 (Box 149)
    - Provost/OVPR, 1996 (Box 149)
    - Rackham/OVPR, 1996 (Box 149)
    - Senior Staff, 1996 (Box 149)
  - Unit Directors Meetings, 1991-1998 (scattered) (Box 149)
  - Unit Oversight Meetings, 1993-1999; 3 folders (Box 149)
  - Unit Projects Group Meetings, 1994-1996 (Box 149)
  - Unit Projects Group Meetings, 1996-1998; 2 folders (Box 150)
- Committees and Task Forces
  - Biological Research Review Committee (BRRC, aka 'Committee C'), 1974-1998
    The Biological Research Review Committee (BRRC) (1 linear foot), which was Committee C of CIVS (Collegiate Institute for Values and Science), was the NIH-mandated oversight committee for recombinant DNA on campus. Formed in a period of intense controversy over the risks and benefits of genetic research, the BRRC responded to public debate on the matter in addition to performing its main task of monitoring university laboratories engaged in such research. In the mid 1980s, as genetic research became more routine, the committee's work slowed down; it met less frequently and 'annual' reports were compiled only every two to three years. This led to a review of the BRRC and eventually to its being retargeted towards human gene therapy research. The later records reflect this change of focus. For more information, background, and committee records, also see the CIVS record group.
    - Recombinant DNA--Background Material, 1974-1976 (Box 151)
    - Recombinant DNA--Debate on Guidelines, 1975-1976; 2 folders (Box 151)
    - Biocontainment Laboratories--Renovation, 1975-1976 (Box 151)
    - Recombinant DNA--Federal Regulations Pre-1986, 1976-1984 (Box 151)
    - Membership Information, 1976-1981 (Box 151)
    - Meeting Minutes, 1976-1982 (Box 151)
    - Annual Reports, 1976-1991 (Box 151)
    - Committee Activities, 1975-1981 (Box 151)
    - Monitoring, 1976-1980 (Box 151)
    - Laboratory Log, 1976-1978 (Box 151)
    - Status of the Committee, 1976-1990 (Box 151)
    - Membership, 1993-1994 (Box 151)
    - Correspondence, 1990; 1994-1996 (Box 151)
    - Human Gene Therapy Initiative Report, November 9, 1998 (Box 151)
    - Regulations and Background, 1986-1996 (Box 151)
  - Classified and Controversial Research, 1971-1999
    The Classified and Controversial Research (3 linear feet) series consists of three subseries: 1) The records of the Ad Hoc Committee on Classified Research, also known as the 'Converse Committee', including reports reflecting the majority and minority opinions of the committee. 2) OVPR files relating to this committee, the situation that precipitated its formation, and the follow-through actions taken regarding its reports. (These records are mostly records of Linda Wilson and Judy Nowack.) 3) Records relating to ongoing classified and controversial research.
    The decisions of the Classified Research Review Panel of the RPC (Research Policy Committee) to accept or reject various proposals by Professors Birdsall, Sinnott, Tanter, et al. led the Regents to call for a review of the University's Classified Research Policy; this in turn led to the formation of the Ad Hoc Committee. Of particular note was Professor Tanter's proposal, which would have studied the ways in which countries negotiated treaties such as those resulting from arms control talks. This proposal was rejected due to the sponsor's (i.e. the Federal Government's) imposition of restrictions and delays on the publication of results. The debate touched on a number of issues, including the openness of research results (and whether any sponsor-demanded restrictions or delays on the publication of results was permissible), the academic-freedom rights of professors to engage in classified and/or military-related research, proprietary research, and the propriety of military research (including Strategic Defense Initiative--aka 'Star Wars'--research) by universities in general.
    Individuals prominent in the records include Professor Philip Converse, Chair of the Ad Hoc Committee; Howard F. Finkbeiner, Associate/Assistant within the OVPR during the mid 80s; and Ingrid Kock, an anti-classified research activist, a student member of the Converse Committee and the MSA's military researcher of the time. The GAO Survey on Department of Defense Labs was the result of an investigation called for by Carl Levin into the oversight of DoD-sponsored research on chemical and biological warfare.
    - Ad Hoc Committee on Classified Research ("Converse Committee")
      - Committee Files, 1985-1987
        (Also includes background material from 1967-1983)
        - Selection of Converse Committee--Various Materials, Fall 1985 (Box 152)
        - Miscellaneous Background Material, 1968-1985 (Box 152)
        - HFF (Howard F. Finkbeiner) History 10/25/1985 and Moyers, Bernstein, and Elderfield Reports, 1976-1981, 1983-1985, 1976-1985 (Box 152)
        - Meeting Notes, November 1985-September 1986 (Box 152)
        - Comments to the Committee, 11/25/1985 (Box 152)
        - Converse Committee Deliberations, 1985-1986; 5 folders (Box 152)
        - Final Report, 716/1986 (Box 152)
      - OVPR Files, 1983-1987
        (Also includes background material from the 1950s-1970s)
        - Solicitation of Comments on Converse Report, 1986-1987 (Box 152)
        - Forums on Classified Research Policy, Fall 1986 (Box 152)
        - UM Classified Research Forums and Discussions, Fall 1986-Fall 1987 (Box 153)
          (In shoebox)
        - Forum Two on Classified Research, 10/23/1986 (Box 153)
          (2 audiocassettes)
          (2 sets)
        - UM Faculty Assembly, undated; 2 audiocassettes (Box 153)
          (accompanies one of the faculty meeting minutes below???)
      - UM Classified Research Forums and Discussions, Fall 1986-Fall 1987
        (In shoebox at start of Box 153)
        - Forum [Three] on Classified Research, 11/11/1986 (Box 153)
          (2 audiocassettes and slides)
          (2 sets of audiocassettes)
        - Hearing on Research Policy Guidelines, March 1987; 1 audiocassettes (Box 153)
        - Regents Research Policy Revision: Discussion and Vote, April 1987; 1 audiocassettes (Box 153)
        - IST Discussion--Regents Meeting, October 15, 1987; 1 audiocassettes (Box 153)
        - Minutes of Faculty Meetings on Classified Research, Fall 1986
          - SACUA, 10/6/1986 (Box 153)
          - SACUA, 11/3/1986 (Box 153)
          - Senate Assembly, 9/15/1986 (Box 153)
          - Senate Assembly, 11/17/1986 (Box 153)
            (agenda and enclosure)
          - LSA Faculty, 12/22/1986 (Box 153)
      - Other Comments and Publicity, May 1986-June 1987 (Box 153)
      - OVPR Correspondence on Regental Research Policy Discussion, 1985-1987; 3 folders (Box 153)
      - Classified Research Expenditures, 1985-1986 (Box 153)
      - Students on Classified Research Projects, 1986 (Box 153)
      - Classified Research: Graduate Student Issues, 1987 (Box 153)
      - Classified Research Practices of Other Institutions, 1986-1987 (Box 153)
      - Classified Research Issues Analysis, 1986-1987 (Box 153)
      - Classified Research Notebook, 1986-1987; 4 folders (Box 153)
        (Distributed to Regents in three waves for October 1986, January 1987 and March1987 meetings)
      - C.I.A.--Includes Investigation of Ingrid Kock's Claim, 1953; 1977-1978; 1986-1988 (Box 154)
      - Policy Implementation Successive Drafts, April-September 1987 (Box 154)
      - Distribution of Implementation Guidelines, Fall 1987 (Box 154)
      - Implementation Guidelines Original, 10/8/1987 (Box 154)
      - Publicity and Discussions, Fall 1987 (Box 154)
      - Classified Research Review Panel--Controversial Proposals and Decisions, 1983-1987
        - DRDA-83-998-P1--T.G. Birdsall, Cooley Elec. Lab.--83-01 (Box 154)
        - DRDA-83-1776-P1--T.G. Birdsall, Cooley Elec. Lab.--83-02 (Box 154)
        - DRDA-84-1558-P1--T.G. Birdsall, Cooley Elec. Lab.--84-01 (Box 154)
        - DRDA-84-1560-P1--T.G. Birdsall, Cooley Elec. Lab.--84-02 (Box 154)
        - DRDA-84-894-P1--M.J. Sinnott, Materials Research Council Project--84-03 (Box 154)
        - DRDA-85-538-P1--T.G. Birdsall, Cooley Elec. Lab.--85-01 (Box 154)
        - DRDA-85-935-P1--T.G. Birdsall, Cooley Elec. Lab.--85-02 (Box 154)
        - DRDA-85-2199-P1--R. Tanter, Political Science--85-03 (Box 154)
        - Classified Research--Kammash, 1987 (Box 154)
    - Miscellaneous Classified and Controversial Research, 1971-1999
      - GAO Survey of DoD Labs, 1982-1990 (Box 154)
        - GAO Survey of DoD Labs, 1987-1990 (Box 154)
        - Schramm, 1986-1988 (Box 154)
        - Lockridge, 1982-1985 (Box 154)
        - Bernstein, 1982-1990 (Box 154)
        - Domino, 1984-1986 (Box 154)
        - Richardson, 1983 (Box 154)
        - Keren, 1984 (Box 154)
      - DoD Mandatory Code of Conduct, 1988-1989 (Box 154)
      - DoD Contractor Reporting, 1989-1990; 1994 (Box 154)
      - FOIA Requests by "Military Researchers", 1991 (Box 154)
      - WCK (William C. Kelly) "Back Pocket" Information on Classified Research, 1992 (Box 154)
      - PAF-R FOIA Requests, 1992-1994 (Box 154)
      - Primate Freedom Tour, 1999 (Box 154)
    - Classified Research Review Committee, Files and background
      - 1971-1976 (Box 155)
      - 1977-1986 (Box 156)
  - GSRA Task Force, 1975-1994
    The records in the GSRA Task Forces (1 linear foot) series reflect several (roughly chronological) waves of activity relating to the status and compensation of graduate student research assistants on campus. Over the years, the various task forces and committees assigned to this area were influenced both by changes in the collective bargaining agreements signed by the Graduate Employee Organization (GEO) and by changes in Federal laws on the taxation of scholarships, tuition reimbursements, and stipends, as well as on cost reporting of federally-supported research. As such, the records include material both on negotiations with (and pressure from) GEO regarding GSRA compensation and on concern from faculty that previously-covered assistant positions would come up short of funding.
    - Committee on Graduate Student Research Assistant Data, 1975-1979
      - GEO (Graduate Employee Organization)/UM Agreement--Requests from Faculty for Assistance, April-May 1975 (Box 157)
      - GEO Contract--Effects on Sponsored Research, 1975-1976 (Box 157)
      - Assistance to Units Employing GSRAs, 1975-1976 (Box 157)
      - Graduate Student Research Assistants, August-November, 1977 (Box 157)
      - Cebulski Report ("A Report on Graduate Student Research Assistants"), November 1977 (Box 157)
      - Graduate Student Research Assistants, 1977-1979 (Box 157)
    - GSRA Task Force, 1986-1987
      - Development of Research Partnership Program, August-October 1986 (Box 157)
      - Cross Report, December 1986 (Box 157)
      - GSAs, 1986 (Box 157)
      - GSRA Peer Survey, March-May 1987 (Box 157)
      - GEO Contract, April-May 1987 (Box 157)
      - Membership and Charge, May-August 1987 (Box 157)
      - Background, April-May 1987 (Box 157)
      - GSRA To Do, April-June 1987 (Box 157)
      - Task Force Notes, May-August 1987 (Box 157)
      - GSRA Options, April-July 1987 (Box 157)
      - GSRA Report--Task Force Comments, June 1987 (Box 157)
      - Short-Term Implementation, 1987-1988 (Box 157)
    - Continuing GSRA Issues, 1985; 1987-1991
      - GSRA Task Force, 1987-1988 (Box 157)
      - GSRA Tax Issue, 1987-1988 (Box 157)
      - GSRA Taxes--Peer Institution Phone Survey, November 1988 (Box 157)
      - Proposed Resolutions to GSA Tax Issue, October-December, 1988 (Box 157)
      - GSRA Appointment Issues (New Tax Situation), 1988-1989 (Box 157)
      - Policy Issues Regarding GSRAs on Sponsored Research, 1987-1991 (Box 157)
      - Administrative Procedures Correspondence, 1985; 1987-1991 (Box 157)
      - GSRA Unassigned Materials, 1987-1991 (Box 157)
      - Graduate Employee Organization (GEO), 1990-1991 (Box 157)
    - Task Force on Graduate Student Research Assistants' Compensation, 1991-1992
      (Includes background from 1988-1990)
      - Charge and Preliminary Material, 1991 (Box 157)
      - Agendas and Materials, 1991-1992 (Box 157)
      - Minutes, 1991-1992 (Box 157)
      - Correspondence, 1991-1992 (Box 157)
      - GSRA Sponsor Costs, 1991 (Box 157)
      - MCare, 1991-1992 (Box 157)
      - RIP (Research Incentives Program) II Data, 1992 (Box 157)
      - Miscellaneous Materials, 1988-1991 (Box 157)
      - AAU Data / MIT Survey, 1992 (Box 157)
      - Final Report--Original and Comments on Draft, 1992 (Box 157)
  - Research Associate Deans (RAD) Group, 1987-2000
    The Research Associate Deans (RAD) Group (1 linear foot) is a group consisting of each School's Associate Dean for Research. The RAD Group serves as an advisory committee to the OVPR.
    - Advisory Council, 1985 (Box 159)
    - Group I and II, 1986 (Box 159)
    - Research Associate Deans Group Meetings, 1987-2000; 13 folders (Box 159)
    - RADs, Fall 2000 (Box 159)
    - RAD Meeting Re: DRDA, March17, 1989 (Box 159)
  - Research Policies Committee (RPC), 1964-2000
    The Research Policies Committee (RPC) (3.5 linear feet in 2002 accession) is an advisory council of the University's Senate Assembly as mandated in the Regents Bylaws. The series reflects several particular interesting aspects of the committee. The records from 1971, during which the RPC held several special summer sessions (and worked in close concert with the Classified Research Committee) to review the University's policies on accepting classified research. Also, OVPR Associate Vice President Alan Price wrote his own set of notes on each meeting, separate from the regular meeting minutes. Finally, the series contains most of the documents distributed to the committee during the period 1988-2000. The record keepers (primarily Judy Nowack, OVPR Research Policy Advisor--circa 1989--and later Assistant VP for Research, circa 1996) conveniently labeled these documents with the date of the meeting they accompanied and the agenda item number to which they referred.
    The 2009 addition to the Research Policies Committee (RPC) sub-series is primarily made up of General Files containing correspondence, minutes, procedures, and other assorted materials. There are also files on promotion procedures for research scientist, and the RPC retreat. The RPC is an advisory council of the University's Senate Assembly, and advises and consults with the Vice President for Research on matters of research and research personnel (http://www.umich.edu/~sacua/rpcindex.html). Researchers should refer to earlier OVPR accessions for additional materials.
    - 1964-2000
      - Membership, 1964-2000 (Box 160)
      - Agendas, 1967; 1970-1971; 1984-1985; 1987-2000 (Box 160)
      - Minutes, 1964-1971; 8 folders (Box 160)
      - Minutes, 1982-2000; 3 folders (Box 160)
      - Correspondence, 1968-1975; 4 folders (Box 160)
      - Correspondence, 1987-1991 (Box 160)
      - Correspondence, 1993-1999 (Box 160)
      - Correspondence and Meeting Documents, 1971; 12 folders (Box 160)
        (Special Spring/Summer Meetings on Classified Research Policy)
      - Associate Vice President Alan Price--Correspondence and Notes on RPC Meetings, 1982-1984; 2 folders (Box 160)
      - Correspondence and Meeting Documents, 1984-1987; 2 folders (Box 161)
      - Documents Distributed--FY, 1988-1992; 1987-1992; 5 folders (Box 161)
      - Documents Distributed--FY, 1993-1998; 1992-1998; 6 folders (Box 162)
      - Documents Distributed--FY, 1999-2000; 1998-2000; 2 folders (Box 163)
      - Professional Service, 1988-1989 (Box 163)
      - Task Force on Diversity, 1988-1989 (Box 163)
      - Minority Research Forum, 1988-1991 (Box 163)
      - RPC on PRS (Primary Research Scientists), 1993-1994 (Box 163)
        (Also see PRS sub-series)
    - 1986-2005
      - General
        - 2000-2001, 2 folders (Box 210)
        - 2001-2002, 2 folders (Box 210)
        - 2002-2003, 2 folders (Box 211)
        - 2003-2004, 2 folders (Box 211)
        - 2004-2005, 2 folders (Box 211)
      - Procedures for Promotion Recommendations for Research Scientists, 1998-2004; 2 folders (Box 211)
      - Retreat
        - 1986 (Box 211)
        - 1987 (Box 211)
  - University Committee on the Use and Care of Animals (UCUCA), 1985-2006
    The University Committee on the Use and Care of Animals (1 linear foot) is appointed by the President to oversee and monitor the University's animal care program, facilities, and procedures. As such, its responsibilities include reviewing applications for the use of animals in research, training, or testing, updating university policies for the treatment of animals, inspecting animal facilities in accordance with these policies, and advising the OVPR on matters related to the use of animals in research and education. The Committee also serves to ensure UM compliance with Federal animal welfare regulations.
    The records of the Committee, compiled by Judy Nowack, consist primarily of the papers (agendas, meeting minutes, and enclosures) distributed to the committee during the period 1995-1997. It also includes the Committee's Semi-Annual Reports to the Vice President for Research for the same time period; of these, the December 1995 report is accompanied by its appendices and supporting documents.
    The 2009 addition to the sub-series consists of reports, statements, and correspondence. The sub-series contains several UCUCA semi-annual reports dating from 1994-2005, but with some gaps. The UCUCA is responsible for monitoring animal care and use at the University, and acts as an advisor to the OVPR. Additional materials may be found in earlier accessions, and in the UCUCA records collection.
    - 1985-1997
      - Meeting Agendas, Minutes, and Enclosures, March 1985 (Box 164)
      - Committee Meeting Materials 1987-1988, 1995-1997 7 folders, 1987-1997 (Box 164)
      - Semi-Annual Reports, 1995-1997; 2 folders (Box 164)
      - Correspondence, 1987-1997 (Box 164)
      - Handout Folder for Rodent Handler Training Session, 1996 (Box 164)